Fatih Sayin

Austin, TX 78729 | (512) 765 3221 | fmsayin@hotmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin/

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

Strategic, multidisciplinary Data Analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Combining my expertise in research methodology, project management, and administrative experience of 18 years with creative data analysis methods to deliver the best results. Aiming of collecting, cleaning, analyzing, visualizing, storing, and making meaningful highlights out of the data with the best tools available.

RELATED SKILLS

- Used fuzzy logic approach for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Proposed solutions to improve system efficiencies and reduce total expenses
- Presented data and analysis in order to improve strategies and operations in academic institutions
- Performed data-driven cultural research to highlight nuances between the general and target business
- Detail-oriented, thorough, initiative, solution-seeker, enthusiastic-friendly team member, and excellent in understanding collaborative project-management to achieve high demands.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization Graduated in 2019

Ivane Javakhishvili State University, Tbilisi, Georgia | Ph.D. in International Relations Graduated in 2009

Free University of Tbilisi, Georgia | BA in International Relations Graduated in 2000

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Python Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions
- Databases: MySQL, MongoDB
- SQL and SqlAlchemy
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, D3.js, Leaflet.j

MOST RECENT PROJECTS

- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

MOST RECENT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

1. Web-Visualization

• Tools Used: Bootstrap, HTML and CSS

• This is an analysis and visualization of weather of 500+ cities across the world. The main objective was to showcase the relationship of various factors like temperature, humidity, cloudiness and wind speed with respect to the distance from the equator.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization

2. Rental Movie Database (Sakila)

Tools Used: MySQL, GitHub

Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql challange

3. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects

- Tools Used: Advanced Excel, Pivot Tables
- Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced excel

4. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude

- Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- Coded a weather API python general script for over randomly selected 500 + cities across the world of varying distance from the equator to detect their temperature, humidity, cloudiness, and wind speed based on their latitude. Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather-Py

5. Name: VBA of Wall Street

- Tools Used: VBA, Advanced Excel, GitHub
- Analyzed Wall Street stock market data in VBA script language.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/The VBA of Wall Street

6. Name: Heroes of Pymoli

- Tools Used: Python, Pandas, Jupyter Notebook.
- Programmed a general python script to analyze the data for a fantasy game. Generated a report that breaks down
 the game's purchasing data into meaningful insights.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes of Pymoli

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Jan 2019 – Present	Investment Consultant and Data Analyst, Cosmos Trading Inc. Austin, Texas, USA
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Improving English Skills, Austin, Texas, USA
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Adviser to the President (in Academics and Investment) Canik Basari University,
	Samsun, Turkey
Sep 2014 – Jul 2016	Founding Director of MIMER (The Alliance of Civilizations Research Center)
	Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Department Chair Department of International Trade and Business Administration and
	IR Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Jul 2006 – Jun 2007	Founding Principal, Nikoloz Tsereteli International School, Tbilisi, Georgia
Jul 2004 – Jun 2006	Founding Principal, Niko Nikoladze Secondary School, Kutaisi, Georgia
Mar 2002 – Jul 2004	Director, Language Center (Enata Tsentri) Kutaisi, Georgia
Jul 2000 – Mar 2001	Director, Language Center (Enata Tsentri) Tbilisi, Georgia

ACADEMIC EXPEDIENCE		
ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE		
Oct 2018 – Present	Data Analytics and Visualization Boot Camp, The University of Texas at Austin	
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Freelance Researcher, Austin, Texas, USA	
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Assistant Professor, Department of International Trade and Business Administration and	
	IR Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey	
Sep 2009 – Jul 2011	Assistant Professor, Department of Business Administration, International Black	
	Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	
Jul 2007 – Aug 2009	Lecturer, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	
Apr 2001 – Feb 2002	Research Assistant, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	

PUBLICATIONS

I have published 19 articles in peer review journals. My academic work includes several articles about the European Union, Caucasus, and Euro -Asia which are published in internationally recognized research journals. I edited the Dictionary of Georgian -Turkish / Turkish-Georgian, which is published in 2012 by International Black Sea University. My latest research focuses on comparative politics, the alliance of civilizations and conflict resolution for global problems. (Analysis of International Conflicts and Possible Solution, Methods Using Fuzzy Logic as an Alternative Perspective) In particular I have been working on the inherent conflicts of political and cultural domination.

LANGUAGES

English Full professional proficiency

Turkish Native proficiency

Georgian Full professional proficiency